all right good afternoon everybody
没事，大家下午好
welcome good to see you so today we're
欢迎好所以今天 我们 看到你
going to look at an idea called
去看看称作思想
exceptional control flow that's a very
异常控制流，这是一个非常
important part of making modern systems
现代制造系统的重要组成部分
and it exists at all levels of the
它存在于的各级
system from the lowest level Hardware
从最低级的 硬件 系统
all the way up to software so the idea
一路攀升到软件这样的想法
is when when you turn on a computer from
就是当你把从 计算机上
the very from the very first time you
很从你第一次
turn it on it just does execute one
打开它，它只是 一个执行
instruction after another until that you
接连直到你的指令
turn it off okay and if each core if you
关掉它好，如果每个核心，如果你
have multiple cores then each of those
具有多个核那么每个那些的
cores are executing instructions one
芯被执行指令的一个
after the other
后其他
now the the sequence of instructions is
现在的指令序列是
called the control flow okay and the the
所谓控制流很好，而且在 该
actual sequence of instructions that the
指令实际序列
hardware is executing is called the
硬件正在执行被称为
physical control flow now normally
物理控制流程现在通常
normally this control flow that executes
通常，执行该控制流程
just one instruction after another just
接连才刚刚一个指令
sequentially in memory and we've so far
依次在内存中，我们到目前为止已经
we've seen two two mechanisms for
我们已经看到了二两个机制
altering the control flow so that it's
改变控制流，以便它的
not so that we're not executing just the
并非如此，我们不是 仅仅 执行 了
next instruction so that's branches and
下一条指令，这样的分支机构和
jumps and procedure call and return okay
跳跃和过程调用和返回好吗
now now jumps and call it branches jumps
立刻跳转，并调用它的分支跳转
call and return those are reacting to
调用和返回那些反应
changes in program State so when you do
改变程序的 状态，所以当你做
a branch you check to control condition
一个分支您检查控制病情
codes and then based on some the results
代码，然后根据一些结果
of that comparison then you then you do
在比较时，然后你再 这样做
the branch okay put it real system needs
分支没关系把它真正的系统需求
to be able to adapt to changes in the
要 能够 适应变化
system State okay so for example data
系统状态好了， 例如 数据
arrives from a disk yep or some are on
从磁盘没错到达或一些上
network user types control C okay the
网络用户类型对照 C 的行
program executes s-- an illegal
程序执行S-- 非法
instruction okay all of these represent
指令还行所有 这些代表
some change some kind of change in the
一些改变某种变化的
in the system state and we need some way
在系统的状态，我们需要一些方法
to react to that so this so what we need
反应到所以这使我们需要的
is we call this exceptional control flow
被我们称这种特殊的 控制流
because it's sort of outside of the
因为它是某种外部的
normal control flow that we we see in
我们看到我们在正常的控制流
our programs
我们的节目
now exceptional control flow or ECF
现在异常控制流或ECF
exists at all levels in the system from
存在于从系统 中 的 所有级别
the very lowest level
最底层
hardware at the very lowest level we
硬件在非常低 的水平，我们
have we're called exception and these
有我们所谓的例外 ，这些
are changes in the control flow in
是在控制流量的变化
response to some low level system event
针对一些低级别的系统事件
so this is a or and bi event we mean a
所以这是一个还是和 双向情况下，我们指的是
change in the state now exceptions are
在现在的状态改变的例外是
implemented using a combination of
使用的组合来实现
hardware and os software which we'll see
硬件和OS 软件，我们会看到
in it in a minute but these these
它在一分钟内，但这些这些
exceptional control flows this at higher
异常控制在较高的流动这
levels to so in the process context
各级 所以在进程上下文
switch is an example of exceptional
开关 是一个异常的例子
control flow that also it's implemented
也它实现的控制流
by hardware and the operating system
通过硬件和操作系统
kernel and it so if process context
核心。它因此 ，如果进程 上下文
switches we'll see later
开关以后我们会看到
later today you're executing your
今天晚些时候你执行你的
executing your code in the current in
执行 在当前代码
your current process and then all of a
您当前的进程，然后所有的
sudden the system is executing code from
突然系统从执行代码
another process right so your process
另一个进程权利，使您的过程
gets like suspended and so there's a so
得到像暂停，所以有这样
that's a form of exceptional control
这是特殊的控制的一种形式
flow where you're executing statements
流在那里你执行语句
instructions within one one process and
一个一个进程内的指令和
then all of a sudden you're executing
然后 突然 你执行
statements instructions in another
在另一个报表说明
process um at a higher level totally in
过程庵在较高的水平 完全在
software we have the idea of a signal
软件，我们有 一个信号的 想法
and this is implemented by operating
这是 由操作系统 执行
system software we'll learn all about
系统软件，我们将了解
signals next lecture and then even
信号下节课再连
higher at an even higher level you have
你 有一个更高的水平更高
non-local jumps in C which are just
用C非本地跳转这只是
implemented by the C runtime library so
C运行时库中实现这样
this allows you non-local jumps allow
这可以让你的非本地跳转允许
you to break the normal call and return
你打破了正常的调用和返回
patterns so from one from within a
图案，从而从一个从内
function normally you can only return to
功能通常你只能回
the function that calls that called you
调用该 叫 你的函数
non-local jumps allow you to within a
非本地的跳跃让你内
function break that and return to some
功能打破，并返回到一些
other some other function or some other
其他的一些其他功能或其他一些
part of the code so we'll look at
代码的一部分，所以 我们来看看
signals and non-local jumps next lecture
信号和非本地跳转下一讲
today we're going to look at exceptions
今天我们来看看例外
and
和
disease so an exception is a transfer of
疾病所以例外是的转印
control to the operating systems kernel
控制到操作系统 内核
where the kernel is the memory resident
其中内核 是常驻内存
part of the operating system you know so
你知道这样的操作系统的一部分
an operating system provides all kinds
操作系统提供 各种
of programs like to list files to change
节目喜欢列出文件改变
directories to list the current
目录列出当前
processes so all of that stuff
流程，使所有 的东西
constitutes the operating system the
构成操作系统的
kernel is the part of the operating
内核是操作系统的一部分
system that's always resident in memory
系统总是驻留在内存中
so an exception is this really low-level
所以一个例外，这真的是低级别
transfer of control to the operating
控制转移 到操作
system because something happened in the
系统，因为事情发生在
system so you're executing your code
系统所以你执行你的代码
user code and then something happens
用户代码，然后有事
some event so by event we need there's
一些事件，因此通过事件，我们 需要有
some change in the system State in
在系统状态的某些变化
response to that there's the exception
针对存在的异常
transfers control from from your user
转让从用户控制
code to code in the kernel which is
代码在其内核代码
called an exception Handler and then the
所谓异常处理程序，然后
kernel responds to that change in some
内核回应了一些变化
way this is called the exception
方式这 就是所谓的例外
processing and then there's three
处理，然后有三个
there's three things that can happen
有三件事情 可能 发生
after the kernel handles the exception
后内核 处理该异常
it can return and re execute that the
它可以返回并重新执行该
current instruction okay and we'll see
当前指令没关系，我们会看到
this is this is useful for things like
这是，这是非常有用的东西 像
page faults allows us to implement
页面错误使 我们能够实现
virtual memory it could return to the
虚拟内存它可以返回
next instruction which I've shown here
接下来的指令，我在 这里显示
or it could abort
或者它可能中止
now exceptions are implemented by
现在异常由实施
hardware and software so the the actual
硬件和软件，以便实际
transfer of control you know the change
控制转移，你知道的变化
in the program counter or IP is is is
在程序计数器或IP是是是
done by the hardware but the code that
由硬件，但代码做到这一点
executes as a result of that exception
执行为例外的结果
is set up and determined by the
设置，并通过所确定的
operating system kernel so every every
操作系统 内核所以每家每户
type of event has a unique exception
事件的类型都有一个唯一的例外
number which serves as an index into a
其用作索引的数
jump table called an exception table
跳转表称为异常表
okay and so when when event K happens
好了，所以当事件发生ķ时
then the hardware looks uses K as an
那么硬件看起来使用K作为 一个
index into this table and gets the
索引此表，并获取
address of the exception handler for
对于异常处理程序的地址
that for that for that exception and so
这对于 该异常等
every time that event K happens that
每次事件发生ķ 当时
handler handler case is invoked now
处理程序处理的情况下，现在被调用
there's a different kinds of exceptions
有一个不同类型的异常
we distinguish them as being
我们区分它们为
asynchronous or synchronous asynchronous
异步或同步异步
exceptions happen as a result of changes
例外情况发生，因为变化的结果
in state that are occurred outside the
在状态发生了外面的那
outside of the processor so these are
所述处理器的外部，以便这些
called interrupts and those changes in
所谓的中断和这些变化
state are the processor is notified
状态，所述处理器被通知
about those changes in state by setting
关于通过设置状态的那些变化
a pin on the on the processor an
上所述处理器上的销
external pin called the interrupt pin so
外部引脚称为中断引脚使
this is the kind of when say a disk
这是那种说的磁盘时的
controller finishes doing a direct
控制器完成这样做的直接
memory access and copying data from the
从存储器存取和复制数据
disk into memory it notifies the
磁盘到内存的通知
processor that it's finished that copy
， 它的完成该副本处理器
by setting the interrupt in hi okay
在喜设置中断好吗
and so after an interrupt happens the
因此中断发生后，
handler returns to the next instruction
处理程序返回到下一条指令
so an interrupt typically it's as though
因此中断通常 这是因为虽然
you're running your program you're
你运行你的程序你
running your program and then there's
运行该程序 ，然后有
like this little there's like this
像这样的小 有这样的
little pause while the interrupt handler
稍微停顿而中断处理程序
runs and then your program just
运行，然后将你的 程序公正
continues to run okay so it's it's
继续 好 运行 ，因此这是它的
usually sort of done behind the scenes
通常 在幕后 排序完成
and doesn't doesn't affect your
并且不不 影响你
execution of your program now the most
你的程序的执行现在最
common a common example of a interrupt
一个 中断 的 共同的 一个常见的例子
is the timer interrupt so you're all
是定时器中断 使你的所有
systems have a built-in timer that goes
系统有一个内置的计时器，去
off every few milliseconds and when it
关闭每隔几毫秒 ，当它
when the timer goes off it sets the
当计时器熄灭它集
interrupts in high and there's a special
中断高 ，有一个特殊的
exception number four for timer
除了排名第四的定时器
interrupts and this is we need this in
中断，这是我们需要在这
order for the this allows we need this
为了使这使得我们需要这个
to allow the kernel to get control of
允许内核得到控制
the system again otherwise a user
系统再次否则用户
program could just run forever in an
节目可能只是在运行下去
infinite loop and no one would be no way
无限循环，没有人就没有办法
for the operating system to get to get
操作系统 去 获得
control so every few milliseconds this
控制，每隔几毫秒这
timer goes off that causes a transient
计时器熄灭， 导致短暂
exception into the into the kernel and
异常进入到内核中，
then the kernel can as we see the kernel
那么内核可以为我们所看到的内核
can decide what to do
可以决定做什么
maybe maybe schedule a new process or
也许可能安排一个新的流程或
let the correct process run and then and
让正确的进程中运行 ，然后和
then this an i/o ended up from an
然后这一个I / O从结束了
external devices is also a common
外部设备也是一种常见的
example now the other classic exceptions
比如现在在等经典例外
are synchronous exceptions and there are
是同步异常和有
three classes of those one is the one
三个班的一个是 一个
class is called the trap a trap is a
类被称为阱的阱是
intentional exception so this is an
故意例外，所以这是一个
exception that's caused intentionally by
多数民众赞成故意所致异常
the program and the most the most common
该方案和最最常见
form of a trap is a system call so you
陷阱的形式是一个系统调用，所以你
know the operating system kernel
知道操作系统内核
provides all kinds of services to to a
提供各种服务，以向
program but your program doesn't have
程序，但你的程序没有
direct access your program can't call
直接访问你的程序无法调用
functions in the kernel it can't access
它不能访问内核函数
data directly in the kernel
数据直接在内核
because that memory is protected and
因为内存保护，
unavailable to user programs so what the
不可用的用户程序有啥
kernel does is it provides a an
内核并为它提供了一个
interface that allows programs to to
接口，它允许程序 来
make request to effectively call
也 求 有效的 调用
functions within the kernel and to make
在内核中，并使功能
requests for various services and this
各种 服务，这要求
this interface is called a system call
这个接口被称为系统调用
okay so a program makes a system call
好了，所以程序 进行系统调用
and and and requests various functions
并和并要求各种功能
from the kernel the kernel provides
从内核内核提供
those sort of reacts to that request and
这些种类发生反应的这一请求，并
then returns control back to the
然后返回 控制回
function there the calling program so
函数 有调用 程序，以便
you can think of a system call as kind
你可以 为一种 认为 系统 调用
of it's a it looks like a function call
它是一个它看起来像 一个 函数调用
but it's really transferring control
但它的真正控制权转
into the kernel okay then there's some
进入内核 好吧，那么有一些
so traps are intentional faults are
所以陷阱是有意的故障有
unintentional but but may be recoverable
无意但却可能是可恢复的
okay so things like page faults which
好吧所以像页面错误 ，其
when we will learn more about these when
当我们将 更多地 了解这些的时候
we study virtual memory but something
我们研究了虚拟内存，但事
like a page fault it's actually
如页面错误 ，它实际上
recoverable it just that the kernel has
可恢复它只是在内核
dirt it means that the data the portion
污垢就意味着数据部分
of the address space that your program
地址空间的，你的程序
referenced isn't actually in memory it
引用的其实不是在内存中
needs to be copied from disk where it's
需要从 磁盘复制它的
stored into memory and then the
存储到存储器中，然后 该
instruction that that caused a fault
指令造成的故障
needs just restarted and then it works
需要刚刚重启， 然后 它的工作原理
that the the memory is is there and then
该内存是存在的，那么
the instruction works properly but other
指令工作正常 ，但 其他
faults are unintentional unrecoverable
故障是不可恢复的非故意
like protection fault so if you try to
像保护故障，所以如果你尝试
access a portion of memory that's that's
访问的存储器的一部分就是这样的
not allocated or floating-point
未分配或浮点
exceptions often times those those can
例外很多时候那些那些能
be recoverable so eat in either case
可恢复所以在这两种情况下吃
when there's a fault it either reacts
当有故障，要么做出反应
Acutes the current instruction or to
Acutes当前指令或
boat or or the boards and then there's
船或或板，然后有
unintentional and unrecoverable
非故意和不可恢复
exceptions which are called the board's
例外，被称为 板的
and those those always the board's
而那些总是那些董事会的
so if you execute an illegal instruction
因此，如果你执行一个非法指令
if there's a problem with your memory
如果有你的 内存 有问题
memory and it's corrupted or if there's
内存，它的损坏， 或者，如果有
some problem with the machine those
一些问题与 那些 机器
creative warts that that always that are
创意疣是始终 是
unrecoverable and never return back to
不可恢复的，从来没有回返回
the to the program now system calls
在该程序现在的系统调用
there's many different kinds of system
有许多 不同 种类 的 系统
calls and they all have their own unique
电话，他们都有自己独特的
number which is assigned by by Linux so
其是通过Linux的分配数，以便
in a for example to read a file there's
在例如读取文件有
a system call called read which is
叫读系统调用是
number 0 opening a file is just an call
打开文件数0 只是 一个电话
number 2 and so on and there's a there's
2号等，并有一个有
an instruction called Cisco which
称为思科的指令，其
actually performs the system call now
实际现在执行系统调用
you usually don't use the system call
你平时不 使用的系统调用
and start desist call instruction
并开始 断念调用指令
directly in your program D Linux wraps
直接在您的节目 D的Linux包
those in system level functions which
在那些系统级功能，其
actually call it for you but it it's
实际上你调用，但它的
interesting to see how it actually works
有趣的，看看它是如何工作
so exactly you want to open a file you
那么究竟要打开一个文件，你
call the system level function called
调用称为系统级功能
open with a file name and some options
与文件名 和一些 选项 打开
say read only write only and so in the
只能说只读，所以写在
cisco instruction takes the first assist
思科指令将第一辅助
call number is in our ax and then other
电话号码是我们的斧头，然后等
other arguments are in our dir si RDX
其他参数都在我们的目录SI RDX
our 10 r8 and r9 so you can see if we
我们的10个R8和R9所以你可以，如果 我们 看到
look in the the open function calls the
看在 open函数调用
underscore underscore open function
下划线强调开放功能
which actually invokes the syscall so if
这实际上调用 系统调用 ，所以如果
you look at that code you see it moves
你看那个代码，你看它的动作
the two which is the sis call number for
二是SIS的电话号码
read into into a ax and then it does the
读入到 一把斧头，然后 它做
SIS call and then the the sis call
SIS呼叫 ，然后将SIS的通话
returns its status in our ax if it's a
返回我们的斧子的地位，如果它是一个
negative number then that means
负数则该装置
something some error occurred
事情发生了一些错误
if it's a positive number then that
如果它是一个正数，则 该
means something that no error occurred
意味着什么没有发生错误
so in this case and I in at the open
所以在这种情况下，我在 开
it's returning as a file descriptor a
它返回一个文件描述符
small integer called the file descriptor
小整数称为文件描述符
which then you you can use in subsequent
然后你就可以在以后使用
calls to read and write and then you can
调用读取和写入，然后你可以
see the code is checking for this
看到代码检查此
negative return value too and there's a
负的返回值太大，有一个
whole series of these compares so let's
整个系列的这些比较让我们
look at an example of a fault
看一个错误的例子
so here's suppose we have this program
所以在这里我们 假设我们有这样的计划
that we're writing into a valid region
我们正在编写成一个有效的区域
of memory but it's not actually stored
内存，但它不是实际存储
on it's not actually in the memory it
它实际上不是在存储它
needs to be loaded from disk into into
需要从 磁盘装入到
memory so this is a so-called page fault
内存所以这 是一个所谓的缺页
so this this instruction this move L
所以这本指令这一举动大号
because this because the memory at this
因为这一点，因为 在这个 内存
address isn't isn't available triggers a
地址是不是不可触发
page fault so that that creates an
缺页，使得创建
exception a transfer of control into the
异常控制转移到
the page fault handler in the kernel
在内核页面错误处理程序
which copies that page from disk to
该副本从磁盘页面
memory and then it returns and when it
内存中，然后返回，当它
returns it re-execute the move L
返回它重新执行移动大号
instruction so that's kind of cool so
指令所以这样的冷却，从而
now the memory is available and now that
现在内存可用 ，现在
the move L this move L instruction when
此举L此举动 提单资料时
it's reacts acute 'add completes and
它是 急性 发生反应 “添加和完成
then we continue now another type of
然后我们继续现在其它类型 的
fault is an invalid memory reference so
故障是无效的内存引用，以便
here we have a we're accessing an
在这里，我们有我们的访问
element of a which doesn't exist and
的元件，其不存在 ，并且
it's an illegal it's an invalid
这是一个非法它是一个无效的
reference so in this case the move L
参考所以在这种情况下，移动大号
instruction it looks like a it looks
指令它看起来像它看起来
like a page fault but the kernel detects
如页面错误，但是内核检测
that it's an invalid address that there
这是一个无效的地址，有
isn't anything that can be loaded from
没有什么可以 从 被加载
disk this is an invalid region of the
磁盘这是 的 无效 区域
virtual address space so it it sends a
虚拟地址空间，以便 它发送一个
signal to the to the process and then
信号给到处理 ，然后
never never
永远永远
turns it so the signal ascent is the
打开它使信号 的上升是
infamous segmentation the signal that
臭名昭著分割信号
causes the infamous segmentation fault
使臭名昭著分段错误
message to print out and we'll see next
信息打印出来，我们会看到未来
lecture we'll see we'll see how these
演讲中，我们会看到，我们将看到如何将这些
signals actually actually work okay so I
实际上信号实际上好工作，所以我
said we've seen exceptions or very
说，我们已经 看到 了 异常或非常
low-level
低级别
transfers of control that are
控制的那些传输
implemented by both hardware and the
通过硬件 和实施
operating system software in kudzu at
操作系统软件 在 葛藤
the higher level is another form of
较高的水平是另一种形式的
exceptional control flow called and we
异常控制流打来电话，我们
see it in the in the context of a
看到它在在的情况下
process context switch so let's look at
进程上下文切换，从而让我们来看看
and let's look at what what a process is
让我们看一个过程是什么什么
so a process the idea of a process is
这样一个过程一个过程的想法
one of the most fundamental and
最 根本的一个和
important ideas in computer science and
在计算机科学的重要思想和
this classical definition of is that a
这一 经典 定义是，
process is an instance of a running
过程是一个正在运行的实例
program okay it's different from a
计划好了这是从不同的
program a program exists can exist in
节目的节目中存在可在存在
many different places right a program
许多不同的地方权的方案
exists in yourseif as text in a C file
在yourseif存在在一个C文件中的文本
it can exist as the dot text section of
它可以作为存在的点文字部分
a binary it can exist as bytes that have
它可以作为具有字节存在的二进制
been loaded into memory a process is an
被加载到存储器 的过程中的一个
instance of a program that's that's
程序的实例就是这样的
running that's in execution and a
运行在执行和
process provides two key abstractions
流程提供了两个关键的抽象
okay it's the first abstraction is that
还好它的第一层抽象是
it gives it gives you the illusion that
它给它 给你的错觉，
you had exclusive access to the CPU and
你必须在CPU独占访问
the and the registers okay so when
在 和寄存器好了，所以当
you're running when you're running your
你当你运行你的运行
program in a process you never have to
程序，你永远不会有一个过程
worry about any other any other programs
担心任何其他任何其他程序
modifying your registers and and you
修改你的寄存器和你
can't even tell that there's even other
甚至不能告诉大家，甚至还有其他
processes running on the system right it
在系统正确的IT运行的进程
looks
容貌
except for occasional delays like an
除了像偶尔延迟
instruction that just takes a little
指令 只需要一点点
longer to run except for that it looks
更长的时间，除了它看起来运行
like you have unique exclusive exclusive
就像你有独一无二的专属独家
use of the of the processor and it's in
使用的处理器， 并将 它在
its registers the the other abstraction
其寄存器的另一抽象
that it provides is the illusion that
它提供的是幻想
you have your own address space okay so
你有自己的地址空间， 所以没关系
you have and this is provided by a
你这 是 由 提供
mechanism called virtual memory so each
机制称为虚拟 存储器，从而每个
each running program has its own code
每个 正在运行 的 程序有它自己的代码
data heap stack and you never see that
数据堆栈和你永远不会看到
the code and you never see the memory
代码，你永远看不到内存
that's being used by other processes
多数民众赞成被其他进程
okay so it looks for all intents and
好了，所以它看起来 对所有意图和
purposes process gives you this illusion
目的过程为您提供了这种错觉
that you have access to the exclusive
你有机会获得独家
access to all the the memory and the and
访问所有的内存和 和
the processor now the the system runs
处理器现在系统运行
many of these processes simultaneously
许多这些方法的同时
even even on a system with a single core
甚至连与 单 核 的系统
many of these multiple processes are
许多这些多个进程是
actually running at the same time
同时实际运行
concurrently and you can see this if you
同时，你可以看到，如果这个你
look at this here I ran top on on my Mac
看看这个在这里我跑顶部在我的Mac上
and you can see it's running 123 123
你可以看到它的运行123 123
total processes five of which are
总流程5可放置
actually running and each one of these
实际运行和这些每一个
processes has its own unique process ID
流程都有其独特的进程ID
this is an integer
这是一个整数
now the way so it looks it looks like
现在的方式，所以它看起来它 看起来像
you have unique access or exclusive
你有独特的访问或独占
access to the to the system but in
进入到系统中 ，但
reality on a suppose we have a single
现实上假设我们有一个单一的
core on a you're actually sharing the
在你的核心实际上是共享
system and the operating the operating
系统和操作操作
system is is sort of managing that
系统有几分是管理
sharing so what it does is that we have
共享，以便他们做的是我们有
a process that's running and it has its
这个过程的运行，它有它的
own it has its own address space and and
拥有它有它自己的地址 空间 ，并
it has its and it has its own registers
它有它的，它有自己的寄存器
and now at some point either because it
现在在某些时候可能是因为它
cut at some point an exception occurs
削减在某一时刻发生异常
either because of the timer interrupt or
要么是因为 定时器 中断 或
a fault of some kind or a trap at some
某种故障或 一些陷阱
point the the operating system gets
点操作系统得到
control of the system and and in this
该系统和并在此的控制
case let's say it decides that it wants
案例让我们说这决定了它要
to run another process so it copies the
运行另一个进程，以便它复制
registers the current the current
注册该电流的电流
register values into memory and saves
寄存器值到存储器中，并保存
them and then it schedules the next
他们然后调度下一
process for execution and it loads the
处理来执行，它加载
the registers that were saved from the
这 是从保存 的寄存器
last time that process was was running
上次那个进程正在运行
it loads those into the CPU registers
它加载到这些CPU寄存器
and then it switches the address space
然后将其切换地址空间
to the address space for for this
地址空间 为这个
process so this the address space and
工艺使该地址空间 和
the register values are the context and
寄存器值是上下文和
so the context switch is is what is the
因此，上下文切换是什么
change in the in the address space and
在更改地址空间 和
the registers ok so then as a point the
寄存器确定，所以然后作为一个点的
that process is running now in reality
这个过程在现实中现在正在运行
on modern systems with multiple cores
在多核现代系统
the operating system will schedule
操作系统将安排
processes on those multiple cores and
关于这些多个内核 进程 和
then if there's no if there's not enough
那么，如果没有，如果没有足够的
course to handle the processes then it
当然，处理过程则
will do the context switching just like
将执行上下文切换，就像
we showed before
我们之前向
now each process represents a what we
现在每一个过程代表了我们
call logical control flow so if you were
调用逻辑控制流，所以如果你是
to you know there's a physical control
你知道有一个物理控制
flow which if we just looked at all the
如果我们只是看了所有的流动，这
TC values we'd be executing instructions
我们会被执行指令 TC值
from one process and then all of a
从一个进程， 然后将所有的
sudden we'd be executing from another
突然之间，我们会从另一个执行
process but within a single process
的过程，但一个进程中
there's a logical control flow which are
有其是一个逻辑控制流
all the instructions for that process
所有该进程的 说明
now we say that two processes run
现在我们说的是两个进程运行
concurrently if their flows overlap in
同时，如果 它们的流重叠在
time otherwise they're sequential so
时间，否则他们是这样的顺序
let's look at let's look an example we
让我们来看看让我们看 一个 例子，我们
have three processes process a runs for
有三种工艺处理的运行
a while and then it's it's interrupted
一段时间，然后是它的中断
by process B and process C and then
通过处理B和处理C，然后
eventually it continues running and then
最终它继续运行，然后
it terminates process B interrupts
它终止处理B中断
process a and then it runs for a while
过程中，然后运行 了一段时间
and then it terminates process C once
然后它终止处理C一旦
when process B finishes then process C
当处理B然后结束处理C
gets to run for a while then process a
得到跑了一会儿， 然后处理
runs for a while and then process C
运行一段时间， 然后处理C
terminates okay so given given this
终止好吗因此，考虑给予这
definition of concurrency which which of
并发 的定义 ，其中的
these processes are running concurrently
这些进程同时运行
what about a a and B yes so so a and
怎么样一个 一个 和B是那么那么一和
these flows B these flow overlaps with
这些流动乙这些流动与重叠
aids flow right so B B finishes starts
艾滋病流 权利，使BB开始结束
and finished some portion this portion
和成品 一些部分该部分
of B's flow overlaps with A's flow like
B的流的重叠用A的流动等
because b is still running hasn't
由于B是仍在运行没有
finished okay so so a and B are
完成好了，那么A和B是
concurrent as and similarly C and a
并发为并且类似地C和一个
overlap so they're concurrent but B and
重叠， 所以他们的并发，但B和
C are not concurrent right these
C 不被并发 这些权
finishes before C starts now this idea
前C结束，现在开始这个想法
of concurrency it doesn't this this
并发 它没有这个这个
definition of concurrency holds
并发的定义持有
regardless of the number of cores right
无论核心数量的权
if even if you have one core this
如果即使你有一个核心的这
example that I showed you was on one
例如，我向 您 展示 了一个
core but even if you have multiple cores
核心但即使你有多个内核
as long as the flows overlap in time
只要流在时间上重叠
they're concurrent but we can think of
他们是并发的，但是我们可以想到的
these no matter what we can we can think
这些不管是什么，我们可以我们可以认为
of these as running in parallel with
这些 作为 平行运行
each other at least from the point of
彼此从点 至少
view of these individual processes
鉴于这些各个过程的
now this this notion of a context switch
现在这个这个概念上下文切换
is it's managed by its managed by the
是它的由它管理的管理
kernel okay and it's important to
内核很好，而且重要的是要
realize that the kernels not like a
认识到内核不喜欢
separate process that's running it
独立过程的运行它
always runs in the context of some
始终运行在某些情况下
existing process and it's it's it's it's
现有的流程和它的是它是它的
just code that's in the upper portion of
只是代码，在上部
the address space that gets executed as
这被 作为 执行的地址空间
a result of an exception so what what
异常的结果， 所以什么什么
happens the way to think about this is
恰好想想这是方法
that you have this process a that runs
您有运行此过程
and then an exception occurs which
然后一个异常发生时
transfers control to the kernel the
将控制权交给内核
kernel invokes its scheduler which
内核调用它的调度器
decides whether to let a continue to run
决定是否让继续运行
or to to do a context switch and run a
或做上下文切换和运行
new process another process so in this
新工艺另一个进程所以在这
example the schedulers decided to to run
例如调度决定运行
process B so it executes code and then
处理B 所以它执行代码，然后
sort of changes sort of once it repoint
排序变化的那种，一旦它重新指向
s' the address space then it's running
S'的地址空间，那么它的运行
in the context of process B and it
在过程B 和它 的上下文
finishes loading the registers for for
完成加载为寄存器
process B general-purpose registers and
处理B 通用寄存器和
then transfers control to B and feed
然后将控制转移到B和进料
takes up where it left off okay and then
占用 它离开的地方好，然后
at some point another exception occurs
在某些 时候会出现其他异常
and in the kernel decides to transfer
而在内核决定转移
control back to process a which picks up
控制返回以处理其拾取
where it left off right here
离开的地方就在这里
so whatever instruction it finishes
所以它完成任何指令
executing whatever instructs instruction
执行任何 指示指令
was executing at the time of the
在的执行时发生
exception execute the next instruction
例外执行下一条指令
here
这里
now Linux provides a number of functions
现在Linux提供了许多 功能
that you can you can call from a user
你 可以，你 可以从用户调用
program to manipulate processes and this
程序操作过程中，这
this this process this act of
这此过程中的这一行为
manipulating processes we refer to as
我们所说的操作流程
process control now all of these
现在过程控制 所有 这些
functions most are I should say most of
大多数功能都是我应该说大部分的
these functions called invokes systems
这些函数调用调用系统
make system calls but they're there
使系统调用，但 他们在 那里
they're wrapped in higher levels what we
他们包裹在较高水平我们
call system level functions that that
调用系统级 功能即是
are the things you actually call from
你实际上是从打电话的事
your user program now system level in
用户程序 在 现在的系统级
Linux system level functions that will
Linux系统级功能即会
typically return a minus one if there's
通常返回一减一，如果有
an error and then they'll set a global
一个错误，那么他们就会设置一个全局
variable called error no to indicate the
变量 称为错误 没有指示
reason so there's a hard and fast rule
之所以这么有一个硬性规定
when you're doing when you're invoking
当你调用当你做
system level functions you must check
系统级功能，你必须检查
the return values from those functions
从这些函数 的 返回值
you should and this you never you'll get
你应该和这个 你永远你会得到
it you'll get into huge trouble if you
它，你会陷入巨大的 麻烦 ，如果你
if you neglect to check the return
如果你忽略检查返回
values okay so you should never make a
值好了，你不应该做
system a system level function call
系统的系统 级功能调用
without checking the return value the
不检查返回值的
and the only exception there's some
而唯一的例外 有一些
functions that return void such as a
返回void如功能
exit or free don't return anything so
退出或免费不返回任何这样
the way the typical way you would do
途中你会做的典型方式
this is like the fork call which we use
这就像fork调用 我们使用
to create processes returns the process
创建进程返回过程
idea of the of the the process that are
的的过程 是理念
created which is always positive if
创造这 始终 是 正面的 ，如果
there's an error returns minus 1 so we
有一个错误的回报减去1，所以 我们
check for the return value to be less
检查 返回值 要少
than 0 and then we we deal with that
比0， 然后我们我们处理 的是
error somehow ok in this case we're just
错误在这种情况下，我们只是以某种方式确定
printing a message and exiting now this
打印的 消息现在这个离开
gets although it's essential to do this
获得虽然 要做到这一点 非常必要
it gets sort of forked from from my
它得到那种从我的分叉
point of view we're trying to present
来看我们试图呈现
code to you
代码给你
it gets really messy it takes up a lot
它变得非常 凌乱 它占用了大量
of space yes
空间是
I'm checking that it's less than zero oh
我检查，它是小于 零的哦
yeah that probably that should be
是的，这大概应该是
normally the convention is to return
通常的惯例是返回
nonzero so you're right that it's not a
非零 所以你说得对，这不是一个
hard and fast rule but that's that's
硬性规定 ，但 就是这样的
typically the convention so I guess it
通常惯例，所以我想这
should be exit one so what we'll do to
要退出一个所以我们会做的
simplify this in the code that we
在代码简化这个我们
present to you and in the code that we
现在你和代码， 我们
present you in the book
目前您在书
well we'll define error reporting
好，我们将定义错误报告
functions so unix-style errors we the
功能，使UNIX风格的错误，我们的
function returns -1 and then sets there
函数返回-1，并设置有
are no will if we get that kind of if we
没有意志，如果我们 得到的那种，如果我们
get that kind of air will will print
得到这样的空气就会将打印
thee will print a message and we'll
你将打印的消息， 我们将
report what that error was before we
报告中，我们之前是什么错误是
exit and so then in the code we can
退出，所以后来在代码中我们可以
replace that that body of that if
更换的该机构如果
statement with just a single line okay
只是一个单一的行语句好吗
so that that makes the code a little
以便 使 一个小的代码
tighter but we'll go even further than
更紧但 我们会走得更远比
that and we'll define these wrappers
这一点，我们将定义 这些包装
which were pioneered by a great
这是由一个大首创
technical writer w richards of stevens
技术作家W¯¯ 史蒂文斯的理查兹
and what we do here is we we replace
我们在这里做的 是我们，我们更换
each function with an error at a wrapper
与包装的误差每个功能
that has the identical interface as the
具有相同的接口作为
function the original function and it
发挥原有的功能，它
has the first the first letter uppercase
有首的 第一个字母大写
and then what this wrapper does is it
然后这个包装做的是什么呢
calls it calls the original function
调用它调用原来的功能
checks for the errors and then and then
检查的错误，然后再
if there's no error returns what the
如果没有返回错误是什么
original function would have returned so
原函数将返回如此
the behavior of this wrapper is
此包装的行为
identical to the wrapped function if
等同于包装的函数，如果
there's not an error okay and if there
有没有好吧，如果有错误
is an error then it deals with it
是一个错误，那么它处理它
somehow and prints a message and so then
以某种方式与显示一条消息，因此然后
this allows us to make our code really
这使我们能够使我们的代码 真的
compact without violating this hard and
紧凑而不违背这个又硬又
fast rule that we have to we have to
我们 必须快速，我们的规则必须
check for errors
检查错误
okay the simplest function process
没关系最简单的功能流程
control functions are functions that
控制功能是函数
allow you to get the pid' for the
让你得到 了 PID” 为
current process which is getpid or the
当前过程是GETPID或
the processor idea of the parent process
父进程 的处理器想法
that created the current process okay so
创建当前处理好了，
this these take no arguments and they
这这些拿不出论据和他们
return an integer which is a process
返回一个整数，其是一个过程
again
再次
now Linux provides ways to create and
现在Linux提供的方法来创建和
terminate processes and from a
终止从工艺和
programmers perspective we can think of
程序员的角度来看，我们能想到的
a process as being in one of three
一个过程如 在三个中的一个是
states running so in this case the
国家在这种情况下运行，以便
process is actually running and execute
过程实际上是运行和 执行
instructions or its it can be scheduled
说明或其它可以预定
maybe it's not running but it can be
也许它没有运行，但它可以是
scheduled at a later time
计划在以后的时间
thanks and it's waiting is waiting to be
感谢和它的等待正在等待
scheduled it can be stopped which means
调度进程可以停止 ，这意味着
that execution is suspended and won't be
该执行被挂起 ，并不会
scheduled until further notice so we'll
计划，直至另行通知，所以我们会
see how this works and we study signals
看到这是如何工作和 我们研究的信号
in the next lecture but usually a
在接下来的演讲，但 通常一
process is stopped because it receives a
过程停止，因为它接收
certain kind of signal and then that the
某种信号，然后将
process becomes stopped in ways it won't
过程变成方式停止它不会
be executed it won't be scheduled until
执行它不会被排至
you explicitly tell it to be scheduled
你明确告诉它安排
oyel process can be terminated which
oyel过程可以被终止，其
means it stopped permanently okay so
意味着它永久停好了，
it'll never be scheduled again it's done
它永远不会被再次安排它的完成
now a process can be terminated for one
现在一个流程可以终止针对一个
of three reasons so one it receives a
有三个原因使一个接收到
signal whose default action is to
信号， 其默认行为是
terminate it or your your program
其终止或您的 程序
returns from the main routine so you
从主程序所以你返回
know you can if you know the definition
知道你可以的，如果你知道 定义
for main is int see main routines always
主数据类型为int 看到主例程始终
return an int so you can return from
返回一个int，所以你可以从返回
main and that will terminate your event
主，将终止您的活动
it will terminate the process or you can
它将终止 过程，也 可以
explicitly call the exit function the
显式调用exit函数的
exit function exits the program with an
退出功能退出程序 用
exit status of the of its argument so
的它的参数，从而退出状态
as as you pointed out that the
只要你指出，
convention is that for normal return is
约定是正常的回报是
to return zero and then non zero on
回到零 ，然后 非零 上
error or you can another way to do this
错误或 您可以另一种方式来做到这一点
is just return an integer value from the
刚刚返回从一个整数值
main routine and that will that will set
主程序和意志，将设置
the exit status now exit is kind of
退出状态 立即退出是怎么样 的
unusual and you'll see this is typical
不寻常的，你会看到这是一个典型
of all these process control functions
所有这些过程控制功能
that they normally functions you call
他们通常的功能调用
them once and then they return one ok
他们一次，然后他们返回一个OK
the exit you call one and then it never
你永远不会调用一个，然后将其出口
returns okay so that's so that's a
返回 好吧，这是如此，这是一个
little unusual now a parent process can
有点不寻常现在父进程可以
create a child process by calling the
通过调用创建子进程
fork function so fork takes no arguments
fork函数所以叉不带任何参数
and it returns an integer it creates a
和它返回一个整数 它创建一个
new child process and then it returns in
新的子进程，然后在返回
both the parent and the child so this is
无论是家长和孩子，所以 这是
a little hard to wrap your head around
有点难以绕到你的头
at first
首先
it's called once by the parent but it's
它是由父调用一次，但它
then it returns in both it creates a new
然后返回在这两个它会创建一个新的
process and then it returns in both the
进程，然后 返回在两个
parent and the child and to the child it
父母和孩子 ，并 给孩子它
returns zero to the parent it returned
返回零到它 返回 父
it returned to the child's process ID
它 回到了孩子的进程ID
okay
好的
the child gets an identical copy of the
孩子得到的相同的副本
parents virtual address space but
父母的虚拟地址空间，但
separate right there they're distinct
单独在那里他们是截然不同的
but immediately after the fork returns
但叉后立即返回
the addresses the address space is
地址的地址空间
identical so that means that all the
相同的，使得指 所有的
variables all the global variables the
变量所有的 全局变量
stack the code everything is identical
栈的代码一切都是相同
and the child
和孩子
it has exact same values as it as it
它具有完全相同的值， 因为它
does in the parent the the child gets
确实在父母的孩子变
identical copies of the parents open
父母开的相同副本
open file descriptors so the child has
打开文件描述符所以孩子有
access to any open files including like
访问包括像所有打开的文件
standard in and standard out that the
在标准和标准出来了
parent had and the only difference is
父母曾和唯一的区别 是
that the child gets a different process
孩子 得到一个不同的过程
ID than the parent so fork is really
ID 比母体所以叉子是真的
strange because it's called once that
奇怪，因为它被称为是一次
returns twice once in the parent and
在父返回一次两次，
once in the child so here's an example
在孩子一旦所以这里是一个 例子
of this here's the this is an example
这这里的，这是一个例子
program that has a it has a local
具有其程序有 一个 地方
variable called X on the stack
在堆栈上可变称为X
initialized to 1 and then it calls fork
初始化为1，然后它调用叉
and fork creates the child and returns
和叉创建子和回报
the it returns a value to that both the
在它返回一个值，无论是
parent and the child we the only way we
父母和孩子 ，我们的 只有我们的方法
can distinguish whether we're executing
是否我们执行可以区分
in the parent or the child is to check
在父母或孩子 检查
that return value okay so here if the
该返回值 好了，所以在这里，如果
process ID is pit as 0 then we're
进程ID是坑为0，那么 我们
executing in the child and remember the
在孩子执行并记住
child got exactly the same has exactly
孩子得了一模一样 具有完全相同
the same memory and and code as the
相同的存储器 和与码作为
parent so X in the child is is 1 so when
所以家长中的X孩子是1，所以当
we print we print this message from the
我们打印我们打印此消息来自
child we increment X and then print this
小时候我们增加X，然后打印此
this message so the child will print 1+1
此消息使孩子将打印1 + 1
2 and then exit
2，然后退出
in the parent when we check that this
在父，当我们检查这
process ID it's going to be non zero
进程ID 这将是非零
because it's the process idea that of a
因为它的过程想法的
child so in this case so so the parent
孩子因此在这种情况下，如此如此父
won't execute this the body of this
不会执行这个这个身体
conditional so the parent will will
有条件所以家长将将就
execute this printf and in the parent we
执行这个printf和父我们
decrement X before we print it so the
减量X之前， 我们打印 所以
parent prints out one minus one is zero
家长打印出一减一为零
now there's no guarantee we have no
现在有没有保证，我们没有
guarantee whether the childhood parent
保证无论是童年父
executes first it could happen when the
先执行它可能发生在
fork when the fork returns the the
叉当车叉返回 的
kernel may decide to schedule the child
内核可以决定安排孩子
first okay in which in which case this
第一没关系，其中在这种情况下，该
code in the body of the conditional
在有条件 的主体代码
would run or it may it may decide to run
将运行或者可能它可以决定运行
the parent first okay and and there's no
家长首先可以的，而且也 没有
way to predict and it is wrong it's an
办法预测， 这是错误的它是一个
error to make any assumption like that
错误做出那样的任何假设
about what's going to run first the
这是怎么回事首先将运行
parent of the child and you can see that
孩子的父母， 你可以看到 ，
they share the same open files because
它们共享相同的打开的文件，因为
both the parent and the child print to
无论是家长和孩子 要 打印
standard out and it prints on the
标准输出，它打印在
terminal okay yes what if the question
终端还好是什么，如果这个问题
is what if you call fork multiple times
是，如果你所说的叉多次
I'll show you some examples of those it
我会告诉你那些它的一些例子
gets a little hairy we'll have a will
变得有点毛茸茸的 ，我们将有一个 意志
use a model called a process graph to
使用一种称为一个过程图，以模型
sort sort of understand what happens
排序排序的理解发生了什么
okay so like just like you said forks
好了，所以像 刚才像你说的叉子
forks or kind of can be kind of complex
叉或种类可以是一种复杂的
and to understand especially if they're
和了解 ， 特别是 如果他们
nested or you call them multiple times
嵌套或者你叫他们多次
so we use the tool called the process
所以我们用所谓的进程工具
graph to to capture sort of what what
图表捕捉到那种什么什么
could happen when we call Forks right we
当我们调用福克斯正确的，我们都可能发生
can we can't we can't make any
可我们不能，我们不能做任何
assumption about the ordering of of
假设有关的排序
different processes but we can capture
不同的过程，但 我们可以捕捉
the partial ordering of events using
利用事件的偏序
this this tool called a process graph so
这本工具称为一个过程图，从而
what we'll do is we'll let each vertex
我们要做的是，我们会让每一个顶点
correspond to the execution of the
对应的执行
statement and then an edge it's that
语句，然后 它是 一个边缘
happens before relation so a happens
之前的关系因此发生情况
for B we will label edges with current
对于B，我们将标签与目前的边缘
values of variables if we have a
变量的值，如果我们有一个
printout vertices a printout a vertex
打印顶点 的打印输出一个 顶点
that corresponds to a printf we can
对应于一个printf我们可以
label that with the output and then
标签与输出 ，然后
every graph starts with a vertex with
每个图形与一个顶点开始
knowing in edges so given this graph
知道在边缘，从而给出该曲线图
then any topological sort of the graph
然后任何拓扑排序的曲线图的
represents some feasible some feasible
代表了一些可行 一些可行
total ordering of events and by
事件 和 总排序
topological sort we mean a total
拓扑排序，我们指的是总
ordering of the vertices where all the
顶点的顺序，其中所有的
edges go from left to right ok so let's
边缘从左向右走OK让我们
look at how this would work for our
看看如何做到这一点 的 工作， 我们的
example program here we have the parent
这里的示例程序，我们有父
initially X is equal to 1 then the
最初X等于 1，则
parent calls fork the fork returns in
父调用fork叉返回
both the parent and the child the child
无论是家长和孩子的孩子
prints and both the parent and the child
打印和双方家长和 孩子
print the value of x after incrementing
打印 x 的 值 后递增
or decrementing and then they both exit
或递减，然后他们都退出
okay so you can think of these as it's
好吧，你 能 想到的 这些，因为它是
happening so these happen concurrently
发生这样 这些同时发生
right which means they can be
正确的，这 意味着他们可以
interleaved and in in any way so the the
以任何方式交错并 因此在
topological sort of this graph will tell
拓扑排序这个图会告诉
us a feasible what's a feasible what are
我们一个可行的什么是一个可行的 是 什么
feasible interleavings ok so we can so
可行的交错 确定，所以我们 可以这样
if we if we real able the graph just to
如果我们如果我们真正能够在图形只是
keep it simple so if we real able these
保持它的简单， 所以 如果我们真正能够在 这些
edges with just single letters then this
只有单个字母那么这个边缘
total ordering a dec FD represented
全序一癸FD表示
represents it's a topological sort and
表示这是一个拓扑排序
thus a feasible total ordering so here
因此，一个可行的总体排序所以在这里
we have a executing then D then e
我们有一个执行则D，那么E
executes sin the child and then at this
执行 罪的孩子，然后在此
point the the kernel decides to swap out
点内核决定换出
swap out e swap out the child and now
换出Ë 换出的孩子，现在
let the parent run so the parent picks
让家长跑那么父精选
up and executes see
并执见
and then and then it gets rescheduled to
然后，然后它被重新安排
chat then the child gets scheduled and
聊天那么孩子被安排和
executes f and then the parent the
执行f和然后父
parent runs and finally finishes right
父运行并最终完成右
so this is this is very unlikely that it
所以这 是这是不太可能， 它
you'd only ask you one instruction and
你只问你一个指令
then and then B and then have a context
然后再B， 然后有一个上下文
switch but it's it's feasible right
切换但它是很可行权
because it represents because the the
因为它代表，因为该
total ordering is it is a topological
总排序是它是一个拓扑
ordering on the other hand this is this
订货，另一方面这是该
is infeasible because F here in this
是不可行的，因为这里˚F在这
total ordering we're executing F before
我们 之前 正在执行 f总播放排序
E and you can see that this that just
E和你可以看到， 这只是
can't happen right so the the edges on
不能发生 这样 的权利 的 边缘上
these the logical flow represented by
这些逻辑流程由下式表示
this child have to occur in this order
这个孩子在这个顺序发生
first E and then F right by that just
第一 E和F然后由恰到好处
because F follows eating the code right
因为F，准备如下吃正确的代码
that the compilers not going to it's not
暂时不会对编译器来它不是
going to alter those
要改变这些
okay so what happens if now if we have
好了，所以如果 现在如果我们有 发生
two consecutive Forks well let's draw
两个连续的福克斯也让我们画
that the process graph will help us
该过程图将帮助我们
understand this
明白这一点
so in the parent we print L 0 and then
所以在父我们打印L 0，然后
fork and that creates a child and both
叉子和创建一个孩子和两个
and so the fork returns to this printf
所以叉返回到这的printf
in both the parent and the child so they
在家长和孩子让他们都
both the parent and the child print L 1
无论是家长和孩子打印大号1
and then both parents and child's
然后家长和孩子的
executes a fork so that creates that
执行一个叉， 使 创建
creates another child that creates two
创建创建 两个 另一个孩子
more now two two children okay and then
现在更多二两孩子 好，然后
and so that returns to the printf which
因此，返回到其的printf
says by so the result of this of calling
通过 这种调用，这样的结果说
Fork twice like this is that creates
叉这样两次 是创建
four processor okay and you can and if
4个处理器没关系，你 可以，如果
it's confusing you can always work it
它混淆你 总是 可以 解决它
out with the process graph like this
不与这样处理图
okay so we can weaken us we can see
好了，所以我们就可以削弱 我们，我们可以看到
feasible and infeasible orderings so
可行和不可行排序以便
this one's feasible take my word for it
这一个可行的把我的话
this one is then feasible and let's see
这是一个可行的，然后，让我们来看看
why
为什么
so it's L 0 and there's no way to to
所以它的L 0，有没有办法来
print by before the first fork all right
第一音叉 没事 前通过打印
so that's infeasible if we if we drew
所以这是不可行的，如果我们如果我们 画
out this process graph we'd have a
这一过程图，我们就会有一个
backward a backward edge
向后向后边缘
okay now what happens if we nest Forex
现在没事了会发生什么，如果我们 外汇 窝
in the parent okay I'm not sure why
在父好吧，我不知道为什么
you'd want to do this except maybe to
你想这样做除了可能 对
torture to 13 students but so we can
折磨到13名学生，但所以我们可以
just work this out by drawing the
刚刚工作了这一点，通过绘制
process graph so here we have the parent
过程图所以在这里，我们有父
it prints L 0 and then it does a fork so
它打印L 0，然后它叉所以
that creates a a child so the child if
创建AA孩子这样，孩子若
fork is not equal to 0 then we're in the
叉不等于 0，那么我们在
parent right so this code executes sin
父权所以这段代码执行罪
the parent if fork is 0 then we're
家长如果叉为0，那么我们
executing the child and the child just
执行儿童和孩子刚
prints by and then and then terminate it
通过再然后终止其打印
eventually terminates I didn't show it
最终结束 我并没有表现出来
here if it calls exit think the function
在这里，如果它调用exit 认为功能
that called this function calls exit so
调用此函数调用退出以
the parent so fork not equal to 0
父所以叉不等于0
indicates that this is the parent so the
表示这是 父，因此
parent prints l1 and then it does
家长打印L1，然后它
another fork that fork creates a child
另一个叉是叉创建一个子
so if if if fork is not equal to 0 then
因此，如果如果如果叉 不等于 0，那么
we're in the parent so the parent prints
我们是在父因此父版画
l2 and then exits this conditional and
L2，然后退出这个条件和
prints by if if fork returns 0 then that
通过如果如果叉然后返回0的打印
means we're executing the child so we
意味着我们正在执行儿童，所以我们
don't execute this code we jump out of
不执行此代码，我们跳出
this conditional and then the child just
这种有条件的，那么孩子刚
prints by ok and we can dub so this this
按OK打印，我们可以复制所以这本
represents an infeasible output from
表示从一个不可行输出
this program
这个程序
l0 Fork week so L 0 followed by by
10 周 叉 使L 0，然后通过
that's feasible and then followed by L 1
这是可行的，然后依次用L 1
that's okay
没关系
and then the next buy is okay but it
再接下来团购是 好的，但 它
simply we can't have this we can't have
只是我们不能有这一点 ，我们不能有
this by preceding this l2 because l2
这个由这L2因为L2前述
will this printf will execute before
将这个printf的会前执行
this printf okay and I'll let you work
这个printf的好，我会让你的工作
out this one up as a as an exercise all
出这一个作为一个练习的所有
right now when a when a process
现在， 当 ，当一个进程
terminates for whatever reason the
终止无论什么原因，
system actually keeps it around for
系统实际上保持它周围
until it's reaped and the reason until
直到它的收获，究其原因 ，直到
it's reaped by its parent and the reason
它是由其父和收获的原因
it does this is that the parent may want
它这是家长可能想
to know about the exit status of the
了解 的 退出 状态
child so but if a parent creates a child
孩子左右，但如果父母创建一个子
it may want to wait for that child to
它可能要等待孩子
finish and and check its exit status so
完成和并检查其退出状态，因此
when when any process terminates the
当任何进程终止时
system leaves that it doesn't it doesn't
系统离开它不它不
remove it entirely from the system it
完全从 系统中 删除 它 它
keeps it or a little bit of state
保持它或状态 的一点点
associated with that child in the form
在该形式相关联的子
of the exit status of the child and the
的孩子和的 退出 状态
and some other tables some other OS
还有一些其他表其他一些操作系统
tables so because this child is
表是因为这个孩子是
terminated but it's not gone it they're
终止，但它不会消失它他们
called zombies so there's sort of half
所谓的僵尸所以有几分一半
half-living half-dead and so a process a
半活半死等的处理的
zombie remains of zombie until it's it's
僵尸仍然僵尸，直到它的它的
it's reaped by its parent using a
它是通过使用它的父收获
function called weight or weighted and
函数调用的重量或 加权和
as a result of as a result of doing
作为因为这样做的结果的结果
weight or weight that the parent has
重量或重量父具有
given the exit status information and
给出退出状态信息和
then the kernel deletes the zombie
那么内核删除僵尸
process now what if the parent doesn't
流程现在如果什么家长不
doesn't read this one of its child
不读其子的这一个
zombies so it's if any parent if the
僵尸所以它如果有父母，如果
parent terminates then the system
然后父终止该系统
arranges for the very first process that
安排 在第一个过程，
existed in the system called the init
在所谓的 初始化 系统存在
process which has a process ID of one it
方法，该方法具有一个 它的进程ID
arranges for the anit process to read
安排在ANIT进程读取
that that child
这是孩子
so there's so orphaned orphaned children
所以有这么孤儿的孤儿
will always be reaped by by the anit
将始终由ANIT可以通过收获
process so we only really have to worry
过程，所以我们才真正担心
about about reaping zombies in in the
约约在收获僵尸
case where we have long-running parents
情况下，我们 有长期运行的父母
like shells or servers because in that
因为像在弹或服务器
case a server may create millions of
区分一台服务器可以创造数百万个
child processes each one of those each
子进程的每一个 每一个
one of those does each one of those
其中的一个确实 的那些中的 每 一个
child processes when they terminate
孩子，当他们终止进程
become zombies and they they have state
成为僵尸，他们自己有状态
which takes up room in the kernel so you
这会占用房间 的内核，所以你
can get this it's a form of memory leak
能得到这个是内存泄漏的一种形式
if you don't if you don't reap these
如果你没有，如果你不 获得这些
zombie children that can eventually fill
僵尸的孩子，最终可以填补
up the memory space and crash the kernel
占用的内存空间，并导致内核崩溃
so for for cases where you have
所以对于 您拥有情况
long-running programs then we have to we
长久运行的程序，然后我们有我们
have to use wait or wait could to read
必须使用等待或等待可以看
the children so let's look at an example
孩子们让我们来看一个例子
first let's look an example of this
首先让我们来看看 这样 一个例子
zombie phenomenon so here we have a
所以这里的僵尸现象，我们有一个
function we call fork and then within
函数中，我们调用fork， 然后内
the child we print a message of the
孩子 ，我们打印的消息
process idea of that child and then we
那个孩子的过程想法， 然后我们
exit the child within the parent we
父我们内退出的孩子
print a message and then we go into an
打印一个消息，然后 我们进入一个
infinite loop okay so this is a parent
无限循环 好了，所以这是一个父
that's that never never reach the child
那是一种永远不会到达孩子
that it created so if we run this
它所创建的，所以如果我们运行这个
program called Forks you can see it
程序调用福克斯 ，你可以看到它
prints these two messages the parent
打印这两个消息的父
prints a message and the child prints a
打印消息和孩子打印
message and then and we're running it in
消息，然后我们在各自运行它
the background with this ampersand okay
这个符号 的 背景 好吗
because we're going to otherwise it
因为我们要否则
would it would it's it's still running
会它会是它仍在运行
and we wouldn't be able to inspect it so
我们将 无法 对其进行检查 ，以便
after we run this program in the
之后我们在运行这个程序
background then we use PS to print the
背景然后我们用PS打印
current processes and we can see that
当前进程，我们可以看到，
there's two we can see here at the
有两家，我们可以看到在这里 的
parent which is process ID 663
父这是进程ID 663
and then the child which is six six four
然后孩子这为六六四
zero and that the defunct indicates that
零和 的倒闭表明，
it's a zombie okay now if we kill six
现在没事了僵尸，如果我们杀了6
six three nine that's the parent and
中6 个九家是父和
then to another PS you see that the
然后到另一个PS你看到
zombies gone that the child is gone
僵尸走了，孩子不见了
because it's been reached by the emit
因为它已经被EMIT达到
process one now what happens if the
现在过程中的一个，如果发生了什么
child doesn't terminate you might wonder
孩子不会终止你可能想知道
like if if a parent creates a child and
就像如果如果父母创建了一个孩子 ，
then the parents and then the chat and
这时家长再聊天和
the child never terminates and the
孩子永远不会终止和
parent terminates then what would happen
然后父终止，会发生什么
much so let's just let's look at an
很多所以我们只让我们来看一个
example of those and see so here we're
那些例子，看看所以在这里我们
we're calling fork we're creating a
我们调用fork，我们正在创建一个
child within the child we print a
我们打印 的 孩子 中的孩子
message and then the child goes into an
消息，那么孩子进入一个
infinite loop and the parent prints a
无限循环 和家长一个打印
message and then exits so if we run this
消息，然后退出，所以如果我们 运行这个
program you can see that the two
程序，你可以看到两个
messages from parents and child and then
家长和孩子，然后消息
if we look at the if we look at the
如果我们看一下，如果我们看一下
prophecies we can see we can see that
预言我们可以看到，我们可以 看到 ，
the child is still running
孩子仍在运行
okay so the channel process is still
好了，所以信道过程仍然是
running even though the parents's has
运行即使父母 的有
terminated and now if we kill this child
终止，现在如果我们杀了这个孩子
six six seven six and then if we kill it
六六 七六 ， 然后如果我们杀了它
then we can see that it's gone it's no
那么我们可以看到，它的消失也没有
longer in the system okay so that child
再在系统好让孩子
when we when we killed it that
当我们的时候，我们把它打死了那
terminated it it had no parents so the
终止它，它没有父母所以
anit process reads it and it it's no
ANIT进程 读取它， 它一点也不
longer a zombie so the the function that
不再是僵尸这样 的功能
we use to to synchronize with children
我们用它来与孩子同步
and read them the simplest one is called
和 阅读 最简单的一个被称为
wait and wait it takes an optional
等待，等待它带有一个可选
status where you can get the exit status
状态在那里你可以得到退出状态
of the inspect the exit status of the
的检查的退出状态
child basically wait suspends the
孩子基本上等待暂停
execution of the process that calls it
调用它的进程的执行
until one or one of its children
直到一个或它的一个子
terminates and it doesn't specify which
终止，它没有指定哪些
one it just waits until one of the
一个它只是 等待 的 一个
children that it created terminates and
孩子们，它创建和终止
then if this child status is not no than
那么如果这个孩子的状态不是 不超过
the integer that it returns are the
它返回的整数是
integer that it points to this is a
整数，它指向，这是一个
pointer the integer that it points to
指针整数它指向
will be set to some value that indicated
将被设置为指示 某个值
the reason the child terminated and its
之所以孩子终止其
exit status and you can you can check
退出状态，你可以，你 可以检查
that using these macros which your your
使用 这些宏，你的你
textbook describes in more detail and
教科书更加详细地介绍和
let you uh so let's look at how how this
让你呃让我们看看如何如何
works in a simple example so here we're
在一个简单的例子作品所以这里我们
calling Fork and creating a child which
调用fork和创建子 其
prints a message and then exits the
打印消息，然后退出该
parent prints a message and then it
父打印一条消息 ，然后将它
waits for the child to terminate and
等待孩子和终止
when the child terminates it prints a
当孩子终止它打印
message and indicating that the child
消息，并表示子
terminated and then prints by so if we
通过这样，如果我们终止，然后打印
were to look at the the process graph of
分别来看看的 过程 图
this you would see that we would have of
这个你会看到，我们 将有
the fork creates the parent and
叉创建父和
the child both the parent and the child
孩子都在父母和孩子
through their their printf and then the
通过他们 自己的printf，然后
parent waits it suspends until that the
家长等待它挂起，直至 发生
child terminates in this case by calling
通过调用在这种情况下，子进程终止
exit okay so what that means is it's
退出好 了，这是什么 意思是它的
it's infeasible so you can say hello
这是不可行的 ，所以你可以打个招呼
from the parent
从父
it's infeasible though for this this
这是不可行的，虽然这本
child terminated message CT to occur
子封端的消息CT 发生
before the bye because
再见，因为前
because the the child hasn't yet
因为孩子还没有
terminated so it these two these two
终止所以这两个这两个
messages will never be printed until the
消息将永远不会被打印， 直到
child is terminated by calling exit so
孩子是通过调用exit终止这样
is that clear yes so the question is can
是明确的 是 这样的问题 是可以
you have an output HP HP HC CT by yes
您 有一个输出 惠普HP HC CT是
yes because the parent ex-prince HP is a
是因为父前王子惠普是一家
context which the child prints HC and
上下文该儿童版画HC和
then exits and now the parent will the
然后退出，现在的家长会的
wait will return and then it prints CT
等待返回，然后 打印 CT
by okay here's this is a and this is a
由还好这里的这是，这是一个
little more go a little more involved
稍微走一点更多 地参与
example so here what we want to do we're
例如所以这里我们想要 做的我们
going to create a bunch of children and
要创建一帮 孩子 ，
then we're going to wait for them all to
那么我们要等到他们都
terminate and we're going to wait but we
终止，我们要等待，但我们
won't be able to wait in any specific
将无法在任何特定的等待
order
订购
we just so here we have a loop 0 through
我们 只所以在这里我们有一个循环0〜
n and in each loop body we're going to
n和在每个循环体，我们要
we're going to fork a child and exit
我们要fork一个孩子和退出
with a return status that that's going
与这回事返回状态
to tell us which child it was in the
告诉 我们它是在哪个子
parent so we do this we do this a end
父母，所以我们这样做，我们做一个结束
time and then and then afterwards the
时间，然后再 事后
parent inside inside a similar loop 0 to
类似的环0到内部母体内
add waits for a child to terminate so
加上等待孩子如此终止
it'll it'll work it will wait for end
它会它会工作它将等待结束
children to terminate wait returns a way
孩子终止等待返回 的方式
return to the the process ID and then a
返回到进程ID，然后
status
状态
which is in in this child status
这是在这个孩子的状态
variable and so we take that variable
可变的，因此，我们采取的是变量
now and we can use this WF exited macro
现在，我们可以用这个WF退出宏
to determine if it terminated normally
以确定它是否正常终止
with an exit by calling exit and if so
通过调用exit如果这样退出
then we can check its exit status using
那么我们就可以用检查它的退出状态
the W exit status macro otherwise if it
在W退出状态，否则宏如果
is WF exit it is false then that means
是 WF退出它是假的则意味着
some something the child terminated for
有些东西孩子终止
some other reason not not because it
因其他理由而不是因为 它
called exits okay there's a we can we
所谓退出还好有一个 我们可以我们
can actually use wait kid which is
可以实际使用的等待 孩子这是
similar to wait but it allows us to wait
类似的等待，但它可以让 我们等待
for a specific process a specific child
对于具体 处理的特定子
a specific process a specific child with
具体处理 的特定的 孩子
a specific process ID to terminate and
一个特定的进程 ID终止并
I'll I'll let you you can wait that it's
我会我会告诉你，你可以等待它的
really involved and it's described in
真正参与和它的描述
detail in your textbook and so you'll
详细的 教材，所以你会
need to look you'll need to look there
需要看你需要看看那里
for the details on how that works now
关于如何 工作的，现在 细节
another important so we've learned how
另一个重要的，所以我们已经学会了如何
to create new prophecy the but we
创建新的预言，但我们
haven't learned how to when we when we
还没有学会如何当我们 的时候，我们
call for it we just create an exact copy
呼唤 它我们 只是创建一个精确副本
of the the child is just an exact copy
的孩子 仅仅 是 完全相同的副本
of the parents running the same code
父母的运行相同的代码
same program same variables okay to run
同样的程序相同的变量好吗运行
a different program inside of a process
的过程的内部的不同的节目
we use a function called exec de and
我们使用了一个名为 EXEC去功能
eggs ik loads and runs within the
鸡蛋IK内的加载和运行
current process it loads and runs the
当前进程 加载并运行
executable file name which is its first
这是它的第一个可执行文件名
argument and file name can be either a
参数和文件名可以 是
binary executable binary okay or it can
二进制可执行的二进制正确的 ，或者它 可以
be a script it can be a text file a
是一个脚本，它可以是一个文本文件
so-called script file that starts whose
所谓的脚本文件启动其
first line starts with a
第一行以开始
pounds bang and then and then there's a
磅砰， 然后再有一个
path of some interpreter so for example
一些翻译所以例如路径
if you if you want to write a shell
如果你，如果你想写 一个shell
script you the first line of your shell
脚本您在外壳的第一行
script is is pound bang and then the the
脚本是英镑的一声，然后将
path name of the bash shell and then
bash shell中的路径名，然后
that will that will execute - and then
将将执行 - 再
bash will will read in the lines
bash将将在读取行
following and interpret them just as
以下并解释它们，就像
though you type them in it's a at the
虽然你 键入他们这是一个在
command line so in either case it
命令行，以便在任一情况下它
executes either an interpreter or it
执行任一解释器或者它
executes the binary with who's argued
执行与谁的 争论 二进制
with the argument list are V and a list
有参数列表 是 V和列表
of environment variables in Eng P okay
在英P环境变量的好吗
now by default argue the first argument
现在默认争论的第一个参数
in our V is the name of the file that
在我们的V是该文件的名称
that's being executed so it's it's this
多数民众赞成执行所以它的它的这个
file name so what that allows you to do
文件名等什么，让你做
is in your code you can check our v-0 if
是在你的代码，你可以 ，如果 检查 我们的V-0
you want to print out the name of the
要打印出来的名字
file the name of the program that's
文件， 该文件的程序的名称
executing you just print out our d0
执行你刚刚打印出我们的D0
okay now at exits all of the code and
还好现在 退出 所有的代码和
the data and the stack it overwrites the
数据，并将 其覆盖在堆栈
completely overrides the virtual address
完全覆盖虚拟地址
space so once you call eggs egg within a
空间所以一旦你叫鸡蛋 蛋内的
within a process it blows away the
一个进程中它吹走
current program that's it okay
目前的计划就是这样好吗
however it retains that it's still the
然而，它保留了它仍然是
same process it's just running now a
同样的过程，它只是 现在运行
different program and so it retains the
不同的程序，因此它保留 了
process ID and any open files that you
进程ID和所有打开的文件，你
have so eggs like is really is really
有这么像鸡蛋真的是真的
mind-blowing because it's called once
令人兴奋的，因为 它被调用一次
but it never returns except if there's
但它永远不会返回，除非有
an error so if this file doesn't exist
一个错误，所以如果这个文件不 存在
for example then then eggs egg will
例如，然后再鸡蛋鸡蛋意志
return on -1 but otherwise in normal
在正常的回报-1但在其他方面
operation it never returns all right so
操作它永远不会返回所有权利，使
let's look at the structure of the stack
让我们来看看它的结构
when this new program starts so after
当这个新的程序启动后使
after after X after the eggs egg ve
X后后后的卵 卵已经
finishes its work it creates a new stack
完成其工作， 它会创建一个新的堆栈
is loads in new code and data creates a
在新的代码加载和数据创建
new empty heath ok everything's new and
新的空荒地 确定一切的新
the stack that it creates has the
它创建的堆栈有
following form ok at the bottom here's
下面的表格 确定在底部这里的
the bottom of the stack and our stack is
堆栈的底部， 我们的堆栈
growing this way so the first function
越来越多这样 使第一功能
that executes is is a function called
执行被称为函数
Lib C underscore start underscore main
库ç下划线开始强调主
so that has it that has a stack frame
使得有它具有一个堆栈帧
so let's look this is what I'm showing
所以让我们来看看，这是我展示什么
here is the situation right before the
这里的情况是 前右
startup code calls main so there's
启动代码调用main 所以有
there's the future stack frame for main
有主将来堆栈帧
will be here at the top of this
将在这里在这之上
following the top of the stack there's
继堆栈的顶部还有的
some padding and then the argument list
一些填充，然后参数列表
in RV is contained on the on the stack
在 RV被包含在堆栈上
so that the RV is a list of pointers
从而使RV是指针列表
terminated by the null pointer and each
由空指针和每一个终止
one of these pointers points up into a
这些指针之一指向了成
string that corresponds to an argument
对应于一个参数串
okay so when you run a program you
好了，所以，当你运行你的程序
specify the
指定